[Music]
this program is brought to you by
stanford university
all right let's uh let's review a little
bit
the basic
equations of cosmology
and then i want to take you through a
little tour of
these equations and what they say about
the structure of the universe
and then perhaps we will get to the
subject of dark matter i want to talk
about dark matter a little bit also
because
most of the matter in the universe is
dark
so
i will
discuss that with you and i will explain
to you in what way it is either
mysterious or not mysterious depending
on your taste
all right well we derived
the friedman robertson walker
the maker i don't know who else equation
from energy conservation
assuming
that the universe was homogeneous
incidentally in this course
i never show these beautiful pictures of
galaxies and everything else
just because um i don't know how to run
the projector up there among other
things
uh
but i will draw for you the universe
the way it would look in one of these
gorgeous gorgeous pictures
you just have to substitute black for
white and white for black and then it
looks like this
it somehow looks better when you invert
the color
and on a scale larger than
the size of clusters of galaxies there
are clusters of galaxies on scales
larger than sizes of clusters of
galaxies millions of light
many millions of light years
uh
the um
many many millions of light years but
not billions of light years smaller than
billions of light years bigger than
millions of light years
the universe looks pretty homogeneous
pretty smooth
okay so assuming that it's good and
smooth
and concentrating on
one galaxy
doesn't really have to be a galaxy it
could just be an imaginary particle
moving along
with the flow
and thinking of ourselves as the center
there's nothing important about where we
are but just to get an orientation
thinking of ourselves as the center of
coordinates
we studied the equations
of energy conservation
for this particle thought of as a
newtonian particle
moving under the influence of gravity
the gravity due to everything within a
sphere
centered on us
and with radius
equal to the distance of the sphere i'm
just going to go through that again
because it's really it's really simple
um
if
we choose
let's put the part let's put the galaxy
over here on the x-axis
and in fact let's put it at x equals one
if it's at x equals one
that means it's distance okay what is
its distance then from us
if it's at and we are of course x equals
zero
its distance is then by definition the
scale factor a
that's the definition of the scale
factor the distance at x equals one the
distance at x equals two is two a and so
forth and so on
so we could concentrate just on this
galaxy by itself that's at that
coordinate x equals one and we can study
how it moves under the influence of
everything else in there
it has an energy its energy is first of
all a kinetic energy of outward motion
its kinetic energy of outward motion is
one half
now its velocity squared its mass let's
also let its mass be one
let's let its mass be one unit
then i don't have to keep writing masses
which just cancel anyway
one half
its mass times its velocity squared and
what is its velocity squared if its
distance is a
then its velocity squared is just a dot
squared where dot means time derivative
that's
that's its kinetic energy what about its
potential energy
its potential energy is minus
the mass contained within here
now what's the mass contained within
here
it's 4 pi over 3
times
that's the volume of the sphere no
that's not the volume of the sphere yet
we have to multiply it by a cubed
that's the volume of the sphere
we multiply that by the mass density
and that's the mass of everything inside
this shell
four thirds pi that's volume
times a cubed
times the density
okay that's the mass in there but
remember the gravitational potential
energy
is
the mass
times g
divided by the distance
let's call it just distance
so
we have to put g in there
the potential energy and then divide by
the distance and the distance is just a
what does newton tell us
newton tells us that this is constant
and independent of time so this is just
some constant and i call that constant i
think i call that constant
minus k
and making it minus k does not
necessarily mean that it's negative k
can either be positive or negative but i
just called it k and
that is the basic equation of cosmology
to make it a little bit more familiar
i don't know familiar or not familiar
depending on your background
first of all we can divide
by
a and make this a squared here
now we can divide the entire equation by
a squared
let's first multiply by two ah wait
let's first multiply by two to get rid
of the half here
that makes this eight pi over three
and i should have called this thing k
only after multiplying by two for
standard the standard notation would
have this being minus k
after i multiplied by two
but in any case it's constant so it
doesn't matter whether i call it k or 2k
now i divide it by a squared and i get a
dot over a
squared that's the square of the hubble
constant
or the hubble none constant
let's shift this over to the right hand
side and that becomes 8 pi over 3
g and i've divided by a squared so this
a squared is no longer here
times the mass density
and then minus k
divided by a squared
the a squared i just divided both sides
of the equation by a squared and this is
the friedman robertson walker equation
friedman f r w l
and everybody else
i'll tell you now although we will
take us to next week next week we will
discuss it in a little more detail the
connection with einstein's equations
i'll just remind you that the einstein
equations in particular the time time
component of the einstein equations
have the form
of some tensor which is composed out of
the curvature tensor what is it it's r
zero zero minus one half g zero zero
times the curvature scalar
uh is equal to what is equal to
t naught naught with a with a constant
in there which is related to uh
there's also some eight pi's and threes
there's also some i can't remember the
exact numbers but i think it has eight
pi over three and g in it
but things of that nature
all right
the connection is simple with this
equation
[Music]
if i transpose all the things without
any energy density in them
a dot over a
squared plus k
over a squared
that's the left hand side of einstein's
equations
if we plug in
an expanding metric
which we'll
write down in greater detail next time
if we plug it in
and calculate the left hand side guess
what we get we get
a dot over a
squared plus k over a squared
and the right hand side we just get
the energy density
rho is of course the mass density but
mass and energy are the same thing
equals mc squared and so
this equation really is nothing but
the time time component of the einstein
equation
uh
i tell you that now just for orientation
that
we have not abandoned albert
for isaac
but at this stage
isaac and albert say the same thing so
we might as well
think about newtonian mechanics
uh to get a first orientation
all right now next thing we did
is we
plugged in
or we
assumed a form for rho for the mass
density and i'll tell you from now on
i'm going to call it the energy density
the energy of a system at rest now why
are we talking about a system at rest
because our coordinates are moving with
the material
so the material in the coordinate frame
that we're using is everywhere is at
rest relative to the coordinates
and uh
under those circumstances
rho
is nothing but the
the mass density at rest or the energy
density at rest
all right so let's uh let's take a
little cube
we take a cube which is one coordinate
unit on the side that means it's
length width and height
our a the scale factor itself
okay
and prescribe how much mass is in there
let's assume there is a mass m in there
there's some value of mass in there
and furthermore under the assumption of
homogeneity on a large enough scale
every cube of the same size has the same
mass so let's just call it the mass m
inside that cube
then what is the density
the density is m
which is constant
the energy in that cube it stays
constant every
masses move but they don't go into or
out of the box and so the amount of mass
in there stays constant but the mass
density
is m
divided by the volume which is a cubed
and that's rho
so now we can write
our
frw equation as a dot over a
squared hubble constant squared
is equal to 8 pi g over 3
[Music]
and now
m this constant m
divided by a cubed
this is not the mass of any specific uh
object it's just the mass within this
cube i call it m
maybe i should have used another letter
for it but it doesn't matter
the mass in the unit cube
minus
k
over a squared
all right we decided last time and i'm
going to continue for the time being
imagining not imagining but using the
empirical fact
it is an empirical fact an observational
fact
that this constant k
is very close to zero it's too close to
zero to tell whether it's positive or
negative
i will tell you now it does correspond
to the curvature of space
but
it's too small to be able to tell
whether it's positive or negative and
it's a very good approximation in
cosmology just to ignore it
and that's
the simple
equation which describes the expansion
of the universe
this is called the matter-dominated
universe it's matter dominated what that
means
is that this formula here corresponds to
a situation
where you have
the energy in this box
just in the form of particles at rest
you count up all the masses in that box
if the masses were moving with a
tremendous velocity there would also be
kinetic energy huge amounts of kinetic
energy in the box
and then we might say that we were
talking about and if the kinetic energy
was bigger than mc squared
or bigger than just m if we set the
speed of light equal to one
that means that the particles are moving
with very close to the speed of light
then we would no longer say it was
matter dominated when one speaks about
matter dominated one was speaking about
the mass distribution being made up of
things which are essentially at rest
moving with the flow
so in that case
for the time being since these particles
since we can think of these as particles
and the particles are not moving we can
for the moment just say the temperature
is zero
and we can also say the pressure is zero
if all the particles came to rest in
this room if the room got so cold that
all the particles came to rest
in the room relative to the coordinates
of the room there would be no pressure
pressure happens when there are
particles crossing the boundaries of
this box
and it will see it is important we're
going to come back to it
but matter dominated
means the particles are at rest in the
box
moving together with the box as the box
flows along with the flow of galaxies
then under those circumstances those are
the circumstances where we should label
this now matter dominated
there may be other forms of energy
around
so there may be other contributions
but in our universe today
well i was going to say if i was going
to say something false
i was going to say our universe is
matter dominated
it is actually not it is dominated by
dark energy but we'll come to that in a
little while
[Music]
but all of the ordinary matter galaxies
protons neutrons
they all add up
and this is the so-called matter
dominated universe the last time we
solved the equations
we solved the equations not by solving
the equations but by guessing an answer
standard
honorable method to solve equations
he said let's try a power law
you might have tried something else you
might have tried sine or cosine or
hyperbolic uh noogie function or
whatever but uh
but
first thing you always try is
a
is a power law
so we tried constant
times
time to a power we plugged it in
what do we find
we found first of all to match the two
sides
to match the two sides
we had to choose p
equal to two-thirds
maybe i should go through that again
very quickly
if this is a
a dot
is cp t to the p minus 1
and a dot over a
is equal to
the c's cancel out and we just get p
over t
square it
and we get
p squared over t squared so the point is
the left hand side
is proportional to one over time squared
the right hand side
is proportional to 1 over time
to the 3p
[Music]
a cubed
goes like t to the 3p
so we have to have t to the 3p
being t squared
that means that p has no choice but to
be two-thirds
so that tells us that the universe
expands as the two-thirds power of the
time
it doesn't expand linearly
a doesn't grow like time it grows like
the two-thirds power of the time
and we can also plug in and once we know
that
then we can plug back into the equation
and compute c if we like c doesn't tell
us very much
it's just if you're doing the
bookkeeping and you want to keep track
of everything
you want to keep track of everything
and if you do
you'll find that c cubed
is equal to 6 pi
m
g
and work it out
this is the more interesting thing here
that the universe expands as the two
thirds power of
of time
what does that look like if we were to
plot it
if we plot vertically
the scale factor
horizontally
time
then
eight uh the two-thirds power
looks uh
i don't know something like this
linear would just be a straight line
this is not as strong as linear so it
turns over like that
okay that's the that's the matter
dominated universe
and
it was the way the universe behaved for
a rather long time
it behaved this way
from about
a hundred thousand years in age
that's pretty young
universe is 10 billion years old
from about a hundred thousand years in
age
to about a couple of billion years
billion or two billion
years or something like that
it behaved according to this matter
dominated law
now
before that
the universe's energy was dominated by
something else it was dominated by
radiation
not by matter so let me explain why the
universe today is filled with photons we
detect those photons most of the photons
are in the microwave range
for the moment we're not going to
discuss where they came from they are
the remnants of the big bang
but let's just take it as a observed
fact
that there are a large number of photons
floating around
in the microwave range
and in fact roughly there are about 10
to the ninth photons for every atom or
for every proton in the universe
so the universe in terms of numbers just
in terms of population
is largely made of photons
on the other hand the photons have very
much less energy than the protons
or even the electrons the protons have
energy mc squared
the photons have no mass
but they do have energy
they do have energy
every photon has energy but let's talk
about that energy a little bit
incidentally when one speaks about the
photon having an energy mc squared we're
talking about the rest energy
how do we get away with saying the
photon has no mass but it has an energy
well we're not talking about the rest
energy of the photon the photon has
energy but it's moving if you try to
slow it down to rest it would just
disappear and would have nothing no mass
no nothing
so um
photons have energy and let's discuss
the photons in
why in the very early universe
the universe was radiation dominated
that means dominated by the inner that
means the energy density was mostly in
the form of photons
why that's true
so
let's begin with the formula for the
energy of a photon
again
we can think of a box
a unit on a side
it's filled up with photons
now photons move
that means photons can pass out through
the box
but on the average there are as many
photons coming into the boxes out of the
box
and so the number of photons pretty much
stays constant in the box
but unlike the protons
the energy
of a photon depends on the size of the
box so let's let's discuss that a little
bit
let's begin with the energy of a photon
the energy of a photon
standard symbol for a photon is a gamma
that doesn't mean it's a gamma ray gamma
rays are just high energy photons
but gamma is the standard symbol for a
photon the energy of a photon
is equal
to planck's constant this terribly tiny
constant 10 to the minus 30 or whatever
it is times what
times the frequency
of the light
that
that that photon is composing
let's call that new
what are the units of new
one over time
yes yes yes yes yes but there's a
there's
yes certainly
hertz
hurts cycles per second cycles per
second
this is also h-bar omega but i'll just
call it h-nu
now we have a wave going by us we have
to
we are necessarily because we're already
we've already studied quantum mechanics
and we're completely familiar with
quantum mechanics completely comfortable
with it
we have no trouble jumping back and
forth from wave to particle picture
right
good okay
so associated with these photons is a
wave
and the wave moves with a speed of light
c
and
if it was
just an ordinary wave in this room
moving past us with the speed of light
it would have a wavelength lambda
a wavelength lambda
and the shorter the wavelength clearly
the clearly the bigger c
[Music]
stand there with your nose watching uh
watching the wave
you're watching the wave go past you and
the electric field goes up and down up
and down and up and down and oscillates
it oscillates with a frequency that
frequency is new it's quite clear the
faster the speed of light is the larger
the frequency the more cycles per second
and the shorter the wavelength the
larger the frequency
so the frequency is equal to the speed
of light divided by the wavelength
so we can rewrite the photon energy
as
h
times c over lambda
the important thing here is the lambda
in the denominator
now what happens to a photon of a given
wavelength as the universe expands
and here is where we will make an
assumption the assumption is very well
justified by
studying the dynamics of electromagnetic
waves
but here
is the assumption
that as the universe expands
the photon wavelengths expand with it
imagine for example
a wave
in a waveguide or in a box
and that wave
is the longest wavelength that you can
have in that box it looks like that
it has no nodes in other words it
doesn't doesn't oscillate just has one
half of an oscillation
what happens is the box grows
as the box grows the wavelength expands
to match the box
it will not jump to a wave with
a node in or with
nodes in nodes mean places where it goes
to zero
won't do that it'll just expand with a
box
as the universe expands it's like an
expanding box
and the wavelength of every photon gets
stretched in proportion
to the increased factor of the scale
factor in other words the wavelength
whatever the wavelength was
if the scale factor doubles then the
wavelength doubles
the wavelength is proportional to the
scale factor
another way to say it well no that's
good enough that's good enough
every photon has a wavelength
that is not frozen in time
but
grows linearly together with the scale
factor
that means
since the wavelength is in the
denominator
and the wavelength is growing
with a scale factor it means that the
energy of the photons is decreasing
as the scale factor grows
and in particular
the energy of any photon
whatever its initial energy was
it will scale
like some constant
divided by the scale factor
as the scale factor increases the
wavelength gets longer the energy
decreases
so we have this box of photons now
there's a given number of photons in the
box on the average it's true they pass
in and pass out of the box but on the
average there's a given number of
photons in the box
every single photon as the box expands
its energy scales like 1 over a
now that means that the total amount of
energy in this box
won't be a constant like m as it was
when we just had
non-relativistic stationary particles
there
but it will scale
like a constant divided by a
now m here does not mean mass it's just
a it's just a label it's just a
parameter
whatever the energy in the box
as a expands the energy will decrease
like a constant divided by a
that's the energy per photon
now
how many photons are in the box let's
suppose that there are in photons
sorry this is
i made a mistake
let's just call this something over a
constant of a that's per photon
but if every photon in the box has an
energy that goes like one over a
and the number of photons stays fixed
that means the total energy in that box
also scales like 1 over a that's the
point so the energy in this box
energy in the box
is some constant
divided by a
now what's the energy density in the box
the energy density in the box you take
the energy and divide it by the volume
of the box
so we divide by the volume
and the volume is a cubed
so that's another a cubed in the
denominator
and what we discover
is the discovery
that the energy of a box of photons as
you expand the box
goes like one over a to the fourth power
instead of one over a cubed
when all we had was particles at rest
we said the total mass in the box was m
we divided by the volume
and we said the mass density
was m over a cubed but for photons
because each photon's energy decreases
as you expand the box
it's one divided by eight to the fourth
okay so let's go back now now we have
now imagine
that the universe instead of being
filled with protons neutrons electrons
ordinary particles moving slowly
let's imagine that the universe is
filled with photons
as i said photons pass through the box
they come in and they go out but we'll
assume that the number of photons in the
box on the average as many come in as go
out
in that case
we have to modify
the equation
which equation
this one over here
we have to modify it
and instead of the right hand side being
m over a cubed it now becomes m divided
by eight to the fourth
so
this is now the radiation-dominated
universe
it looks pretty similar a dot over a
squared equals same thing
pi
g over 3
and now the energy density which instead
of being m over a cubed is a constant
which i called m again
different constant
divided by a to the fourth
it even has different units now
well can we solve that equation yeah we
can solve that equation we do it the
same way
let's plug in let's
make a trial solution
a equals
c
t to a p to the p
again
a dot over a
is just
p divided by t that's a dot over a
p divided by t
we square it
p squared over t squared
that's the left side now let's go to the
right side
8 pi g over 3
m
and now a to the fourth so now i'm going
to have in the denominator
c to the fourth
that's not going to be very interesting
but t to the 4p
[Music]
eight to the fourth is c to the fourth
times t to the 4p
and now
if i'm going to match both sides
this one goes like 1 over t squared as
time goes on
this one goes like 1 over t to the 4p
4p had better equal 2 otherwise they
can't match
okay so
4p had better equal two or p equals one
half
so we've discovered that the radiation
dominated universe
expands
not like t to the two-thirds but like t
to the one-half
square root of t in other words
this expand and we can also calculate
the constant c i'll leave it to you to
calculate the constant c it's not very
interesting
oh i'll tell you what c to the fourth is
32 pi over three times g n
that was not very illuminating to me
either
but
the fact that the universe expands like
t to the one-half power instead of t to
the two-thirds is somewhat interesting
okay
yeah
why is your g in there there's always a
g in uh
this is yeah this is the gravitating
effect of energy
remember
in newton's theory
yeah
okay good that's a good question
we discussed it last time but let me
come back to it not last time last
quarter
newton's theory is the theory of things
moving very slowly compared to the speed
of light
the dominant form of energy when things
move with close or slow compared to the
speed of light is just the mass the m c
squared energy
that's
you may think of m as being simply the
energy plus a little bit of kinetic
energy may be there
all right when things move near the
speed of light
then the energy
is not proportional to the mass
it's more complicated for example
photons
which have no mass do have energy
but the right hand side
or the thing which gravitates the thing
which pulls the thing which causes
gravity
is not rest mass it is energy when the
object is slow then its energy and its
mass are the same
a rapidly moving photon
will gravitate will cause uh will cause
things to be pulled toward it another
example here's an example take a box
and fill it with lots and lots of
radiation
radiation so so much radiation that it
would melt the walls of the box but
let's make
walls that won't get melted in our
imagination
and we fill this box with a huge amount
of radiation
that box will gravitate more than the
box without the radiation in it it will
have more energy
e
if the box is at rest its energy is the
mass times uh and it will gravitate it
will gravitate and pull things toward it
so it's energy which is the thing which
gravitates
uh
when we're writing this equation here
this doesn't really stand for mass rest
mass it stands for energy density
okay
so it's energy density which gravitates
and it gravitates proportional to
newton's constant g
okay
is either of these equations solvable
with an a that decreases with time
oh yeah in fact i mean if you put back
the one over a square the k over a
squared term
you'll find examples where it increases
and then decreases
or maybe we'll do that
uh for the time being it's not too
important because there's no i mean it's
it may be important conceptually for
some reasons but uh
the universe does not appear to be doing
anything like that yeah but the equation
well there's a solution equation
yeah
what happens to the energy you say the
energy per photon so the total energy
goes down what happened to conservation
of energy no no no this equations are
conservation of energy
this is kinetic energy
let's put back let's put back the k or
the k and multiply by a squared
these equations state conservation of
energy but there's two kinds of energy
one of them are the ordinary things such
as photons and protons and neutrons and
everything they go on the right hand
side
the left hand side is the energy of
expansion it's the energy of the
gravitational field it's the thing which
is left out until you know about general
relativity
okay
so
these are well actually what is it it's
really the kinetic energy of the uh
of the outward moving things here's
kinetic energy here's the energy
uh of the object
in a frame of reference in which it's at
rest
so in other words this is the rest
energy of a box moving with the flow
and this is its kinetic energy
it's the sum of them which
which is conserved and if you said it
if you set it equal to zero in other
words if you set this minus this equal
to zero that's surely conserved
so it's a balance between two kinds of
energy kinetic and potential
just the
assertion about
it's the energy that's doing the
gravitating
it's the other kinds of it yeah that
is not clear until you go to general
relativity i mean that's that's right
that's correct right you might have
guessed it from special relativity e
equals m c squared you might have
guessed it um
in fact einstein did guess it that's
exactly how i guessed it what he did
what he did was he
first examined he studied a box of
photons like this
and he said what's the mass of that box
of photons
all right so here was his thought
experiment he said let's push on that
box of photons when you push on the box
of photons
just take the box by itself
it takes a certain force to accelerate
the box because the box has a mass
but now when you start to accelerate the
box
more photons hit this side of the box
than hit that side of the box because
you're pushing the box
this wall is moving away from the
photons this wall is moving toward the
photons and so you actually have to push
a little bit harder
to push against the pressure the
radiation pressure in the box
that means effectively the mass of the
box is a little bit bigger and einstein
worked it out and he found that the
extra mass the extra inertia of the box
was in fact proportional to the energy
of the photons in there
that was the origin of v equals m c
squared
now he also had rather early the idea of
the equivalence principle
that um
that gravity works the same on all
objects
and from that he came to the conclusion
that the earth would pull on this box
as if it had a mass not equal to just
the mass of the original box but the
mass plus the photons in there
but if the earth pulls on the box the
box pulls on the earth etc etc so rather
early he had the idea that energy
gravitates
okay it took him a while to get it all
together
and ultimately yes it's the general
theory of relativity
which tells us that
that it's
energy which goes on the side
right
remember last quarter we talked about
having to make tensor equations
and the left-hand side of einstein's
equation is a tensor the right hand side
is the energy momentum tensor
composed out of energy and momentum
okay um
so
we have
two kinds of cosmologies
real cosmology is a combination of both
of them
but let's try to understand
under what circumstances
and when
and at what times
the universe might be matter dominated
and when it might be radiation dominated
in fact it is a question of when whether
the universe is matter-dominated or
radiation dominated the reason is the
following
i just explained to you that as the
universe expands
the energy density of radiation
decreases
but it follows that when the universe if
you imagine contracting it going
backward
the energy density of radiation must
have been much larger
if you squeeze it it's larger if you let
it right so at some point
when the universe was really squeezed
where the wavelengths of all the photons
were really small
the photons had more energy than the
ordinary matter yeah
so
as universe ages does the p
go go continuously from one half to two
thirds
not abruptly for sure but uh you know
more or less uh in a fairly narrow range
of time
it doesn't jump i was going to say it
jumps it doesn't jump it goes
continuously
from
one half to
two thirds
well i was about to draw give you a
rough idea but let's uh let's let's just
plot just to
get the idea up on the blackboard
all right
let's first plot energy density
e density
and let's draw both cases
the matter dominated here's the matter
dominated
it looks the matter energy density
and that goes
it goes to zero and
it does go to zero how does it go to
zero
it goes to zero like one over a cubed
it also becomes infinite when a goes to
zero this is let's see um this could be
yeah this is um a
a on the horizontal axis
scale factor
when the scale factor goes to zero
that's the situation where the universe
is shrunk to a point
the density becomes infinite
all right
now that's the this is the matter energy
density let's write matter out here
and then there's radiation the radiation
is one over eight to the fourth
one over eight to the fourth is smaller
when a is big
but bigger when a is small
so one over eight to the fourth looks
like this
and at some point they cross
at some point
the
matter density becomes less than the
radiation density
so sufficiently early if we go back far
enough
the universe was radiation dominated
okay
what does that mean in terms of um
exactly what was asked before what does
that mean about the growth of the
universe
it means it started out early
we'll try to estimate in a moment where
this happens
when that happened
in a little while
all right
if i plot now i plot something different
i plot the scale factor versus time
okay the scale factor versus time here
was
energy versus the scale factor here's
the scale factor versus time the scale
factor for radiation dominated
goes like the square root of time
t to the one-half and that looks like
this and let's extrapolate it
okay
but at some point where this crossover
happens
it's a bad approximation beyond that to
say that the universe is mainly
radiation the energy
it becomes mainly matter at that point
and not
it's not a sharp point
there's uh a region in here
it makes a transition from t to the one
half from square root of t
to t to the two thirds
t to the two thirds is bigger than t to
the one-half
and so that's what the universe looked
like for a fairly long amount of time
the interesting question
is where did that point happen
okay so
we can talk about that a little bit now
oh no before we talk about that let's
talk about temperature let's talk about
temperature
i want to talk about the various
interesting things which happened
one of the things which happened was
this transition
from matter from radiation dominated to
matter dominated that happened after
about ten thousand years roughly
speaking
something like about ten thousand maybe
a little more than ten thousand years
ten thousand years after the big bang
okay
something else happened which is
actually observationally more dramatic
what happened to the photons if you run
the universe backward to early times if
you run it forward their wavelength
grows
if you run it backward their wavelength
shrinks what happens to the energy of
the photon as you run it backward
increases
what does that mean about the
temperature of the universe goes up
it goes up in fact
to a good approximation the temperature
of a black body
of the temperature
of a box of radiation
is basically just the energy of a single
photon
it differs by some numerical factor
so
apart from some trivial numerical factor
the
temperature
of the radiation
this is the temperature of the photons
which are moving around through the
universe
they have a temperature
and their temperature
changes with time
it goes like 1 over a now when i say it
goes as 1 over a i mean i just mean it's
proportional to one over a
if a doubles the temperature becomes
half as big if a quadruples the
temperature is
one quarter is big and so forth so the
bigger a the smaller the temperature the
smaller a the bigger the temperature and
just proportional to one over a
okay now that means as we trace backward
there was a time when the temperature
was much hotter
in fact there was a time when the
temperature was as hot as the surface of
the sun
[Music]
the surface of the sun is rather
different
visually than
the space around it in particular the
sun is opaque
you cannot see this
it's not because the sun is too bright
to see the stars behind it
that's not why you can't see the stars
behind it you can't see the stars behind
it because the starlight
hits the sun hits the material of the
sun and gets absorbed into the sun and
gets rattled around and just gets
absorbed by the sun
rather than transmitted through the sun
the sun is opaque
why is it opaque
it's opaque because it's ionized
ionized means that the atoms have been
separated into positive and negative
charges
an ordinary atom is electrically neutral
because an ordinary atom is electrically
neutral
it means that an electric field doesn't
accelerate it a vibrating electric field
doesn't uh doesn't do much to the atom
it may cause the atom to change size and
shape a little bit but it doesn't it
doesn't accelerate the atom because the
atom is neutral
but if the atom were replaced by a
proton and an electron let's say a
hydrogen atom
if the atom was replaced by a electron
and a proton
freely moving not bound to each other
the electric field would slosh the
electrons back and forth it wouldn't
slosh the protons as much because the
protons are heavier
so when an electric field
passes through an ionized material
it sloshes the electric charge back and
forth and when it sloshes the electric
charge back and forth
the electric charge behaves as an
electric conductor and electric
conductors are opaque it's the reason
that a mirror is opaque why can't light
go through a mirror why does it bounce
off because the light hitting the mirror
drives electric currents and the
electric currents radiate the signal
back
so a ionized material
is very opaque
if you heat up
hydrogen and in fact we haven't
discussed it very much yet what was the
universe made out of what is the
universe made out of mostly hydrogen
[Music]
universe is largely hydrogen it was even
more hydrogen in the past hydrogen and
some helium
but uh if you go back early enough the
temperature was high enough
that the helium and hydrogen were
ionized electrons were pulled off the
atoms
and it was opaque it was hot and opaque
in fact it looked it was about like the
surface of the sun
okay
let's ask when that happened see if we
can figure out when that happened
well there's a particular
temperature
what's the temperature of the photons
today
three degrees
today's temperature
temperature today
is very cold
three degrees
absolute zero above absolute zero
okay what is the temperature near the
surface of the sun anybody know
3000 degrees something like that 3000
degrees about a thousand times larger
about a thousand times larger
so the temperature
at which
the gas ionizes let's call that the
ionizing temperature
and it's also more or less the surface
of the sun
that's about 3000 degrees
well
if the temperature
varies
like 1 over a
as a gets smaller and smaller the
temperature goes up
that means that at a time of ionization
the universe must have been the scale
factor it must have been a thousand
times smaller than it is today
the temperature scales together with the
scale factor
as one over a
if the temperature today is a thousand
times colder than it was
at ionization
[Music]
that means the universe must be a
thousand times bigger
let's see if we can figure out when that
was
at what time that was
let's define a time let's remember the
following now
the scale factor
grows
like t to the two-thirds today
t to the two-thirds doing the matter
dominated
era
the late times were matter dominated
after the universe cooled down a bit
all right so a grows as two-thirds
what this tells us
is that the time to the two-thirds today
divided by the time
at which ionization happened to the
two-thirds
must be about a factor of a thousand
the scale factor today is a thousand
times bigger than it was at ionization
the scale factor is proportional to the
t to the two thirds
and so
this tells us that the scale factor
today to the two thirds power
divided by the scale factor at
ionization to the two thirds power
must be about a thousand
right we know what the time today is
what's the time today this is today
about 13.5 billion years
it's about 13 point that we measure by
measuring the hubble constant that tells
us how fast the galaxies are moving
apart if we run it backwards it tells us
how long it was since the galaxies were
sitting on top of each other
13.5 billion years
let's call it 10 billion years
this is 10 billion
so this is
10 to the 10th
to the two thirds well let's let's uh
let's see what should we do
if we take um
no
if we take the three-halves power of
both sides it becomes t today
divided by t at ionization
is equal to one thousand
to the three halves
i've taken the three half side of both
equations the three-halves side of
something to the two-thirds to just
cancel out
what's a thousand to the three-halves
uh what's the square root of a thousand
is about thirty
so that's about thirty 000 right
yes
yeah
yeah it's two
it's a thousand
[Music]
to the one plus one half
a thousand to the one is a thousand the
thousand to the one half is thirty
thirty thousand
okay so that's thirty thousand three
times ten to the fourth
in years
no sorry just it's not in years three
times ten to the fourth
okay so that tells us that t ionization
let's just solve that for t ionization
t ion
the time when ionization happened
if we run it backwards
is equal to t today
that is 10 billion years
10 to the 10th
uh divided by 3 times 10 to the fourth
right
are you rounding it down
13 is 10 okay
13 is 10.
we can uh adjust it later
all right so 10 to the 10 divided by 10
to the fourth is 10 to the sixth this is
10 to the sixth that's 10 to the fifth
times 10 divided by 3 10 divided by 3 is
so that's 300 000 years
after 300 000 years
before 300 000 years
the universe was completely ionized
it was completely opaque light could not
travel very far
there was a dense plasma
of
torn apart
atoms
the nuclei
were mostly
hydrogen with a bit of helium
and uh
the main thing is it was hot and opaque
as hot as the sun as the surface of the
sun and
opaque like the sun
now let's let's uh let's think about
what that means to an astronomer
it's an astronomer with a very good
telescope
here's the astronomer at the center of
the universe and the astronomer looks
out
and as he looks out he looks into the
past
all right so if he looks uh to um to the
next galaxy
the andromeda he's looking about two
million years into the past that's not
much if he looks out to
some distant galaxy out here he's
looking further into the past
and the shells
are both
distance as well as uh
time
backward in time as you go further and
further out
well as you go further and further out
the temperature
of the photons is increasing
[Music]
the temperature locally
out here
to a traveler who is traveling with them
is higher than over here because he's
looking back into the past and as you
look back into the past
the temperature was higher
eventually
at some
distance
namely about 13 or 10 13 13.5 billion
light years
he sees back to the point where the
universe is ionized
so and out beyond that the universe is
completely ionized
and light cannot penetrate it it just
scatters around light just scatters
around in here
and then
at some point as you move in
it becomes cool enough for atoms to
recombine
for atoms to recombine and become
unionized for the electrons to get
trapped by the protons and form atomic
hydrogen and atomic helium
at that point the universe becomes
pretty transparent
why is it transparent because it's not a
plasma anymore so way how far it's a
plasma
out to some place
no of course it's a fuzzy place it's not
a sharp place
it's a fuzzy place where the universe
goes from being a plasma to being a uh
or a time at which the universe went
from being a plasma to being a uh a
clear
system with just uh some neutral atoms
at that point light can travel through
the universe without scattering very
much
this surface
where you go from plasma to
ordinary gas is called the surface of
last scattering
that's the surface of glass scattering a
photon rattling around there
will come to that surface of last
scattering and then pretty much be able
to freely move through the universe
so when we look out all the things that
we normally see
are on the inside of the surface of last
scattering and we can't really look out
beyond the surface of less scattering
not with electromagnetic waves anyway
yeah
so that's okay so basically what you're
saying is our limitations with our
telescopes radio et cetera
they cannot look
beyond 3 300 000 years ago that's it you
know
not 300 000 years ago but they can't
look back right earlier than 300 000.
now are there other things that can look
back yes
neutrinos are electrically uncharged
they don't get scattered by the
by the ions in there neutrinos just pass
through an ionized gas
eventually it gets hot enough
that even neutrinos interact with each
other strongly
so there's some other shell out here
that's the surface of last scattering
for neutrinos
but with the neutrino telescope which
doesn't exist of course
such a thing doesn't exist
but with a neutrino telescope if you
could see the very low energy neutrinos
then you would be able to see deeper
into the past
a graviton telescope could see even
deeper into the past but why when we
look out in the sky and we look up here
don't we see the surface of the sun in
every direction
[Music]
this is a modern form of ober's paradox
if it's true that out here
everything is as hot as the surface of
the sun
why don't we look out at the night sky
and see
the bright glare
this is not
standing still relative to us
it is moving away from us
with very close to the speed of light
and that means that every photon and its
way in here has been red-shifted by a
factor of a thousand
that's what made the temperature go from
three thousand degrees to three degrees
so what we look out and we see
is microwaves
of
temperature three degrees
that's not much of a signal a three
degree uh black body
you don't see it three thousand degrees
if you looked out in every direction
you'd burn your eyeballs
uh
so
when neutrons separate into
protons well say it again when
a moment of last scattering from
neutrinos when the uh the neutrons and
electrons uh
protons and electrons no i think it was
earlier than that um
it was at the time when the weak
interaction was as strong as the
electromagnetic interaction which was a
good deal more energetic
[Music]
you know i don't think that that's
and uh right and the gravitons even
further back but they're even harder to
see
and what
i mean what makes them hard to see is
the same thing which allows them to get
through this junk
the reason they get through the junk is
because they're so weakly interacting
you can see that sphere
that's what you see in the cosmic
background variation you see this sphere
right i'm talking about the neutrinos i
mean that certainly
we do in fact see that oh yes this is
yes yes yes
yes that is what you see when you see
the cosmic microarray background
absolutely yeah yeah
yeah yeah
all the way to the beginning what is
that gravitons why would why would there
be a shell for rabbits
what a deal
oh gravitons become strongly interacting
with each other when the energy gets
high enough and when the temperature
gets high enough
what would be the
distance from the
big bang to that point the planck
distance
the planck distance
10 to the minus 33 centimeters
right 10 to the minus 42 seconds
so well the point the point that i was
raising though was
it's the same thing which makes them
be able to get through this junk which
makes them hard to detect
they're hard to detect because
everything is transparent to them
including the detectors
right
yeah if i understood correctly that the
surface of the sun is where it seems to
be because that's the temperature at
which
light would become opaque to light so
that's why the sun is the size it
appears to be that's that's the
temperature at which the which the
ionization
which it's called recombination where
the atoms recombine now why is it as
sharp as it is the sun has a fairly
sharp edge when you when you look at it
um
and the answer happens to be the
exponential behavior of the boltzmann
distribution and i didn't want to get
into that today but uh but on that same
subject when you talk about the
temperature of a photon
you're talking about the temperature of
a black body whose central rate whose
peak radiation is that temperature yeah
correct but that is not linear
the temperature the temperature is
essentially the energy
of the average photon
okay the average energy the photon has
an energy which is one over its
wavelength
so yes the temperature is one over the
wavelength of the uh the radiation
no no no no that's energy density
that's not the energy of a single photon
t to the fourth is either the energy
density or the uh
[Music]
uh
or the uh energy flux the luminosity
yeah
yeah d to the fourth is
as a combination of the energy per
photon and the number of photons per
unit volume
okay
so in order to find the energy density
of a black body you have to know the
energy per photon and the number of
photons per unit volume
the number of photons per unit volume
goes like p cubed
and the energy of a photon goes as t and
that's what gives you t to the fourth
altogether
yeah
neutrinos
don't have any intrinsic motion i mean
the the they move with very close to the
speed of light the photons you can't
stop them
so they're always going but but aren't
the neutrinos that are
aren't they sort of attack
just go to they had a box full of
neutrinos doesn't that same
why are they moving
our matter is not moving relative to the
boxes uh that are that are growing with
this with the rate of the universe
photons move yes the photons
what about neutrinos
why do neutrinos move
well the first approximation they're
massless so they're very much like
photons
they have a teeny teeny teeny tiny mass
so they have to so they're very high so
so you can't treat them their energy is
much larger than their mass you can't
treat them
like as numerology particles they have
to be treated separately
for practical purposes you can treat
them as being like photons
yeah
a neutrino would have to have a very
very very low energy in order for it to
be moving much slower than the speed of
light
so you know it's only recently it's only
in the last several years
that people have really been able to
measure the mass of the neutrino because
it's so small
and for all practical purposes not all
practical purposes but for many
practical purposes neutrinos just move
with the speed of light
so these original
neutrinos also are very cold in some
sense or another
no they were hot they were hot no now
now now they're probably about a little
bit colder than the photons maybe two
degrees
uh
but similar to the photons do you know
what uh what time after the big bang the
scattering for neutrinos uh yeah i would
have to say that but it's it's
microscopically small it's much smaller
yeah
we'd have to do we'd have to do some
work
is that why it's two degrees cooler
because that surface is farther ahead
well the surfaces um no it's uh it's
cooler
yeah it decoupled earlier and uh
yeah
then stuff happened that was out of
equilibrium and heated the photons it
didn't heat the neutrinos
so
so i nobody of course has ever measured
the neutrinos
um people i believe estimate something
like two degrees but it will be a little
bit colder yeah
how about dark matter with that also
okay now we want to talk about dark
matter
now let's talk about dark matter
all right um
all right dark matter
was not discovered
by studying cosmology where cosmology
means you know the universe uh as a
as a whole
cosmology means the study of things
bigger than a few billion light years
anything smaller than that is astronomy
and then they've invented this this word
um
if it's ugly astronomy ugly difficult
astronomy uh meaning to say that it's
not neat and elegant and they call it
gastronomy
that's not my word
yeah
all right so
um
the dark matter
which certainly has an important
cosmological
consequence very important
but it was not discovered by
cosmologists looking at cosmology it was
discovered by uh
by astronomers looking at galaxies
and so galaxy is a small object on the
scale of the whole universe
and measuring what are called the
rotation curves of the
of the galaxy
the rotation curves are simply the rate
at which
things move around the orbital velocity
of stars at different distances from the
center
so let's start with orbital velocity
and let's go all the ways back to the
solar system
just to get a handle on orbital
velocities
the solar system or
any system which is composed of a
central mass
and then orbiting
one or more orbiting uh
planets let's call them
all right
now what i'm interested in
the the mass of the central object is m
the things orbiting around it are
considered to be lighter
and i want to know the velocity
of an orbiting object as a function of
its radius as a function of its distance
from the center
the
orbiting object let's say the orbiting
object has a mass little m
okay
let's see if we can work it out
what we use is newton's equations f
equals m a
what is the and we're applying it to the
planet
right
what is the force on the planet the
force is due to the sun at the center
it doesn't have to be the sun just some
central object and some orbiting
planetary system
the force is m
m
g
divided by
r squared right
where r is the radius of the orbit
that's the force and it's directed
radially inward
that's equal to the mass
times the acceleration so we have to
know is the acceleration of an object
moving in a circular orbit
i'm going to write down the answer
the acceleration of a circular orbit is
toward the center
it involves the velocity and the radius
anybody know the formula
v squared over r
i am not going to prove that we're just
going to check its dimensions
what's the dimensions of acceleration
dimensions of acceleration
are length per unit time per unit time
length per unit time squared
velocity per unit time is acceleration
velocity is length over time per unit
time
let's just check that velocity squared
over r has the same units
velocity squared has length squared over
time squared
and r has length
so hopefully
these have the same units they do
okay
it's a true fact that the acceleration
of a circular orbit is toward the center
same direction as the as the force and
it's proportional to the velocity square
equal to the velocity squared
divided by the radius of the orbit
okay so let's do some cancellation
the little m's cancel out
which means that the acceleration
doesn't depend on the mass of this
object
we can multiply both sides by r
and then we find that the velocity
is equal to the square root
of mg
over r
in particular the velocity of a distant
planet is smaller than the velocity of a
centrally located
velocity of
neptune
or pluto is much smaller than the
velocity not just the not just the
angular frequency but the actual
velocity
falls off as one over the square root of
r
now if you look at galaxies through a
telescope
what you see
of course is light
and it was always believed
that the amount of light coming from a
region
was proportional to the number of stars
in that region and so forth so it'll be
proportional to the amount of mass in
that region
and galaxies are
mostly
cores the center
and then there are these
some galaxies are spiral arm galaxies if
you look at them from the edge they look
like that
but most of the light
and most of the
material the observable material
the light matter light matter means the
matter that you can see because it glows
because it gives off light
most of it
is in the core of the galaxy
so
if you were to just
take literally
that mass follows light
that the mass distribution is comparable
to the light distribution
and look at gal and look at stars
at different distances out here
they would mostly be moving in the field
of a central object similar to the
similar to the center of a solar system
if that were the case now we can also
look down on this from above it's a core
a very diffuse bunch of stuff out here
that doesn't have much light coming out
of it and we can
everything moves around
all right we can measure we can measure
the velocity
of stars
in such galaxies or we can measure the
relative velocity
we can measure the overall velocity of
the receding galaxy
is a relatively nearby galaxies
we measure the overall recessional
velocity and then we measure the
difference between the velocity of this
point and that point we discover that
this point is moving toward us this
point is moving away from us
and in that way uh compare it with the
overall velocity
we can pretty well calculate
the velocity of
orbiting the orbital velocity not
calculate measure the orbital velocity
of stars as a function of the distance
from the center
and what do we find not me but what do
the people who do this kind of work fine
they find
that the velocity does not fall off
like 1 over the square root of r
instead it's pretty constant
the velocity of
not the angular value takes longer to go
around far away but that's because
there's a longer distance but the
velocity of a star over here
is about the same as the velocity of a
star over here is about the same as the
velocity of a star near the outer edge
of the of the galaxy
so there's something wrong with this
picture of a galaxy that it's mostly
composed of matter near the center
right so you can do something else
and say wait a minute now let's let's
see if we can figure out
where the matter really is
maybe maybe mass doesn't follow light
maybe the light distribution is not a
good sampling of the mass
so let's use what we do know about these
velocities to see what we can say about
how the mass is distributed
okay
now think of
let's suppose now that the mass is not
concentrated at the center
but it's distributed in some way
it's distributed in some way and from
simplicity
let's say it's distributed nice and
symmetrically
then what mass should we be using in
here
for a planet or not a planet for a star
at distance r from the center
what mass should we be using
well we should be using all of the mass
out to a distance r
[Music]
remember a planet or a star moving at a
certain radius feels all the mass inside
that shell so we can correct this
formula and we can say
let's correct this formula
and say the right formula
is m of r
times g m of r times g
the meaning of this m of r
is it's the amount of mass
in a sphere of radius r
so far we've not assumed anything
particular about that distribution of
mass we've just assumed
that there's a notion a functional
motion of the mass within a sphere of
radius r
this formula is very general of course
it also doesn't say anything
you don't know what m of r is but you
measure v
but v
you discover is constant you discover
that all of these velocities are the
same
so what does that say about m of r
it grows linearly with r
the amount of mass out the distance r
[Music]
is proportional to r
so the amount of mass
in a sphere of radius r
apparently
grows
like r
what about the density of mass does that
grow
no we have to divide by r cubed if we
want the
if we want the average density of mass
the average density of mass
we would want to divide by r cubed
and no it doesn't mean that the density
that it gets denser and denser as you go
out
but it does mean
that there's a halo of mass out there
which is more pronounced that that most
of the mass of the galaxy is out far out
near the edges and maybe even beyond the
visible galaxy
right
now you say okay we can use the velocity
to actually
tell us what m of r is
we can
we can figure out using the velocities
we can tell what the mass out to a given
distance r is and we can compare it take
the whole galaxy
out to its very extremities
we know what the mass distribution is
just from these uh from the rotational
speed of the stars
and we can say how much mass is there
altogether
how much mass is there in this hidden
unobserved mass
in the hidden unobserved mass that does
not follow light
it's not proportional to the light
there's about 10 times the mass
that would that we would normally
associate
with stars and luminous objects
that produce the light of the galaxy
in other words the estimate
of just saying that the galaxy is made
up of stars
or
luminous matter like stars
captures only about a tenth of the mass
of the galaxy the galaxy is at least 10
times heavier yeah
that's that's correct so
there could still be more dark matter
yeah
uh
i think that um
that's true
that's
that is true i may be
i think what's true is the total mass
that's expected to be in a galaxy is
about 10 times the the mass of the
luminous matter
it does of course fall off when you go
far enough away
but you're right out to the out to the
boundaries it
it follows this dark matter curve and i
believe the total mass of a galaxy is
roughly about 10 times what you what you
what you see with light
let's see is that right um
yeah i think it's approximately 90
percent yeah
what
no dark energy is about thirty percent
darken uh darker ordinary matter is four
percent dark matter is thirty or forty
four yeah so it's about ten ten to one
ten one is about
right dark uh
dark matter
luminous matter is what about four
percent of the hole
and uh
and the dark matter is probably another
thirty percent
so it's something like a factor of ten
or seven or something like that
four times seven is 28 yeah
but for some galaxies there's evidence
that a lot of the dark matter is beyond
the last luminous yeah yeah but i think
i think the total amount of it is about
10 times the mass of the galaxy total
amount but some of it extends out beyond
the galaxies
i'm not an expert at this incidentally
but how the density it looks like the
density sort of go one over r squared
well yeah you can have a reason for uh
uh let's see no nobody
i don't
this is not something that uh that's um
subject to anything except uh
simulations and you know simulations
account for some of it but i don't know
these ratios true for all galaxies and
galaxy like structures
so again variation with some
some in some
some yeah i think for all big galaxies
yeah
uh yeah it's pretty much the same we can
calculate what the density is let's see
the density is such here's the if you
have rho which is the uh the density
let's do it a little bit better
rho of r
now if you integrate rho of r
now what do we have to integrate it with
to find the mass within a shell
by r
4 pi r squared
in particular
r squared d r right
and you're right four pi and i don't
care about the four pi
this is the thing which uh
is equal to one
you integrate it from zero to capital r
and this is the total matter the total
mass
within radius r and this is the thing
which grows as r
okay
so
how would you solve this equation
well we can differentiate but we can
differentiate both sides of it with
respect to r what happens when we
differentiate an integral with respect
to r
you just get the integrand right
so we get rho of r
r squared
is equal to 1.
rho of r
looks like 1 over r squared
row of r is 1 over r squared
but there's a lot of matter out there
and about 10 times what's in the
galaxies what do we know about it it
doesn't shine
so that's one thing
it doesn't produce light
another thing we know about it
is it didn't contract it's it's it's
much bigger halo than the size of the
galaxy the galaxy is a fairly small
thing
embedded in a big halo of this dark
matter
the dark matter is in a form of a
spherical halo
even if the galaxy is in the form of a
um of a disc galaxy of some sort
at least that's expected and it's i
think even observed
uh
that
so
it's a big
globular blob of mass that has not
contracted together with the uh with the
um
with the luminous matter to form a
smaller more concentrated thing
what is it that causes
the
contraction
of a bunch of gas to
to a smaller
lower the temperature
no no no no no no no it shrinks it
shrinks when it shrinks the temperature
goes up that's why stars form
[Music]
when it shrinks the star it goes up
it's a friction dissipation of some
thought or another some form of
dissipation some sort of collisions some
sort of uh friction
is the thing which uh which causes
if you just started with a ball of gas
and the gas is going back and forth and
back and forth oscillating some of it's
going around in a circle
nothing much happens to it it just stays
about that size
it shrinks because of collisions and
because of radiation it radiates away
energy it shrinks
and
you know interesting kinds of collisions
and processes have to happen in order to
cause it to shrink
well ordinary matter has plenty of
different kinds of processes in
particular radiates light
and the radiation of light causes it to
collapse
and other kinds of processes collisions
between
atoms and so forth
whatever this stuff is out there it's
very collisionless
and it doesn't radiate light
so it's very weakly interacting somehow
it doesn't do very much other than
gravitate
doesn't that make it unstable unstable
structure
no because it would break from any force
to collapse what keeps it out there
kinetic energy
okay what keeps
what keeps the uh what keeps um the
earth going around the sun
why doesn't the earth fall into the sun
no friction
right but there's a little bit of
friction so the earth is slowly falling
into the sun
and at one time there was more friction
which caused the primordial gas cloud to
coalesce and condense into things
[Music]
so whatever this stuff is out there it
has a lot less friction than other
matter yeah is this a porous at a
distance or is it a is it a spherical
shell
no it's not a shell it's it's a sphere
but whose density goes down like one
over r squared
not a taurus
taurus be very hard to know it's not a
taurus it's a sphere
a large spherical blob
yeah
possibility of intergalactic dark matter
um or dark galaxies
dark galaxies
you mean just a blob of dark matter yeah
i mean it would gravitate so yeah
neutrinos just wouldn't behave that way
they're moving too fast
a ball well it's not it's not a uniform
ball it's a
a ball yeah
yeah
a ball which is more dense in the center
but the density doesn't suddenly fall
off like the light does
it gradually falls off
one of the times
how do you how do we know that
there's dark matter outside the luminous
stars you see going around and you can
measure the velocity of the
other different arms the galaxy and and
say how much matters inside
that
i don't know
but you can yeah you can tell you can
you can roughly estimate the mass of a
galaxy by looking at the motion of other
galaxies in the vicinity of the galaxy
so
uh
what's that
well colliding galaxies but just uh just
the motion of uh the i don't know i
suppose the motion and the magellanic
clouds and things like that uh tell you
something about the total mass or
although
so um it must be
the motion the relative motion of uh
of nearby galaxies which give you some
hint at what the total mass of the
galaxy is the black hole would not be
counted as dark matter
no no no no dark matter's very
definitely collapsed you mean could it
be a bunch of
of of uh of black holes
uh
people have talked about that
and i think the general conclusion is no
um
but i'm not uh really sure exactly why
would there be lending if a massive
thing
it would be less yes there'd be lensing
there'd be lensing but also if those
black holes originated from ordinary
matter
it would say that in the primordial
universe before those black holes formed
there was a lot lot more ordinary matter
out there and that would be deadly for
nuclear synthesis and
and the the origin of the elements
so
the best bet i think i think the best
bet by far is that there are elementary
particles which are very weakly
interacting
um
galaxies seem to have net angular
velocity oh absolutely um
but they're not as flat or they're not
the
dark matter is not as flattened as uh
as the galactic uh plane would indicate
presumably they have the same
net angle
not necessarily not necessarily no i
don't think so i don't think that where
does the angular velocity come from of
the uh
well i mean you know the angular the
angular velocity of the solar system is
not the same as the angular velocity of
the sun in fact the angular velocity of
the solar system is not exactly well
defined
not exactly
oh oh um
yeah yeah good
yeah i would say that the angular
i don't know
er i don't know what's known about the
rotational motion of the halo i don't
know
the dark matter the dark matter hero
that's a good question
anything about it at all i i don't know
the answer whether anything is known
about the rotational motion of the halo
decreasing energy what's that
is the dark matter decreasing energy
decreasing energy in what's happening in
the dark matter the energy is decreasing
decreasing with respect to what prime
time
uh why would it be decreasing it's
pretty much staying the same it's not
changing very much
it doesn't interact with anything yeah
it doesn't lose kinetic energy what
about dark energy
that's another question we haven't come
to that uh
we can
when you're estimating the ordinary
matter in a galaxy if you add up all the
planets and the oort cloud and creeper
belt and all that stuff in a solar
system
how big a fraction of that is the
of the total mass of a solar system
negatively small
[Music]
conservation of anger momentum from the
big bang it seems like if there wasn't
any net angular momentum of that initial
mass and you have different galaxies
they would net out to have to not have a
greater angular momentum
so
does that come into play with with also
the net angular momentum of are you
remembering whether the uh the angular
momentum of galaxies shows some
alignment is that what they're asking
well that that i mean they all couldn't
be spinning clockwise from look for at
one direction
i would have been
but from that point of view that would
that can you conclude anything about the
angular momentum of these dark matter
clouds that they would also have to
balance to
well i think you probably
i think it's pretty uh pretty darn
certain that they average out on the
average but whether the angular velocity
of whether
i think the question was is there some
locking which locks the
the
visible galaxy to the halo
i think that was the question i don't
know
i will try to find out i don't know
presumably angular velocity of the the
galaxy came from something that happened
you would think that at least
at least they probably point in the same
same direction
but even that i don't know
and i don't know if it's measured uh
it's a good question i really don't know
the answer
the dark matter what's that the dark
matter shallow dependent on the light
matter
report
well it seems like the dark matter is
more the primordial thing that uh that
coalesced
um
[Music]
it was probably the first thing to start
uh
coalescing into well-defined structures
and the ordinary matter probably
followed it got trapped by it but then
the friction of the ordinary matter and
collisions caused it to sort of continue
to shrink while the dark matter being
largely transparent to itself
didn't shrink except the only thing that
affects the dark matter is gravity
gravity is enough to cause it to
condense and start to shrink and and
start the only common denominator is a
gravity what's that it's the only common
denominator between the line
yeah that's the only that's the only
serious interaction between them well
then where do all the kinetic energy
come from that's keeping it from
collapsing it doesn't interact
except for gravity you said kinetic
energy is keeping it from
collapsing where does that energy come
from from potential energy
originally started originally started
with a pretty uniform distribution but
don't think of it as uniform
distributions just think of it as very
large
diffuse blobs of gas
very very large and very diffuse
and they did gravity pull them together
gravity caused them to contract
and they contracted some
and the process of contracting
potential energy got converted to uh to
um
uh
[Music]
is it the case
i just had a question here about the
mechanics is it the case if you have a
particles that don't interact except
gravitationally and they're in a disk
it's unstable and it must be i suspect
the disc is unstable so it has to evolve
to a a glo
well radially varying but other than
that a uh
yeah now how the this how the globe the
globular structure manages to stabilize
the disc-like structure in it that i
don't know
uh
maybe related to polarity
to what to the polarity that uniform
polarity within the galaxy
what does the polarity mean
magnetic polarity oh it doesn't have to
do with magnetic fields it doesn't have
to do with magnetic fields i don't think
i don't think so
even that i don't know for sure
this is this is really the subject of uh
people who do large-scale simulations
is this less direction than the disc and
there in
in a more and more random orbits
because in if they're rotating the disc
they run into each other
much less often than they do if they're
if all the orbits are going oh why are
we haywire
every which way yeah i'm sure it's true
so it seemed to be that that
at least
in some chance that a dissipative
process would leak
lead to
a disc-like structure well it certainly
did in the solar system
and around saturn
so i don't know i'm beyond my pig right
now i'm not enough i'm not enough of a
gastrophysicist to know the answer to
these questions yeah
how do they get an estimate for the
amount of dark matter between the
galaxies
well i think from the relative motion of
the relative motion of the galaxies
themselves is sensitive to the material
between them
i thought most of dark matter was right
around the galaxies there wasn't much
well it's spread out something like
like this
and how far that goes out does it
continue like that
until you get to the next galaxy sort of
or does it uh or does it tail off and
then a flat region in between i don't
know the answer
uh the question let's see a galaxy is
how big is the galaxy
hundred thousand light years right
something like a hundred thousand light
years and the distance to the next
galaxy is about a million light years
two million light years something like
that
so
uh
basically the
dark matter within the clusters of
galaxies has no uniform distribution
it's like clouds in the sky there's
more dance and less dense reasons yeah
and
it's
it's just
the progression of the gow to the motion
of the galaxies within the cluster
the point being what well they they
mapped out
the
density
the relative density of the dark matter
within the clusters and they show these
clouds of stuff supercars random in
nature which says that
the galaxies collect it and it goes by
the one over r squared but
that either
increases or decreases when they pass
through each other oh that's for sure
but uh you know how how it's distributed
in the region you know halfway between
the galaxies i don't know
yeah getting back to the single uh
galaxy model that you have up there
and most uh galaxies have a super
massive black hole or a black hole but
that's a very small fraction of the mass
of the coil there's any way we can we
can uh
analyze the
dark matter in that
perspective in terms of black hole
i think the dark matter is rather unif
is so diffuse and spread out over such a
large distance that i don't think
it uh
black hole is a tiny little thing at the
core so i don't think so
uh there's uh
on dark matter
well there are limits there are various
kinds of limits on the nature of the
particles which might be the dark matter
particles
just by looking at the motion of the uh
i don't know how accurately measuring
the motion of the planets but we can see
general relativity but i wonder if you
can see that you mean is the dark matter
appreciably affecting the gravity of the
solar system i don't think so
no
what's the respirator are they i mean
how do if they don't interact except for
gravity what sort of experiments are
they putting up to try to detect well
when you say they don't interact i mean
or maybe they just interact for a week
leaving yeah i mean
um
if an electron passes through a lump of
lead it will uh interact with a lump of
lead every single time
if a dark matter power particle passes
through a lump of lead it may interact
with the lump of lead 1 out of 10 to the
13th times or something well you just
let 10 to the 13th dark matter particles
pass through and you'll discover one of
them
so you just use the statistics of large
numbers
and you know there are lots of detection
schemes that are out in place there for
searching for dark matter
thus far
they're always out of the range of
detectability
wouldn't there be a signature of dark
matter in falling towards the black hole
to the horizon
well it's too diffuse
it's very diffuse
is there any reason to believe that the
dark matter is essentially in circular
orbits i mean again you'd have to get
this
i don't think there's any reason to
believe it's a circular it's probably
not certain probably not in circular
orbit i don't think there's any reason
so there could be some very very uh
highly elliptical orbits yeah there's
probably things like that
some of the dark matter could in fact
just by accident run into the uh
the
black hole sure
sure but it's very diffuse i mean
so so ex extremely elliptic orbits are
eliminated by the black black hole at
the center
but the black hole is a tiny tiny tiny
little geometric object at the center of
the uh of the galaxy
so you're eliminating
very very little bit that way
yeah no i i think there's no reason to
believe that the orbits are circular the
orbits
the orbits
are probably all over the place some
circular some elliptical some very
elongated some of them just going back
and forth except not hitting the uh
can they be deflected by a neutron star
and every other masses it's reflected by
they preserve yeah they pass uh pass
through most things yeah i don't know if
they pass through a neutron star but
they probably uh
pass through the earth very easily
right
if you had the uh some sort of
statistical uh probability distribution
on the types of organs then you could
probably get the row of r as one over r
squared maybe
no i right
no i don't think there's any um easy way
to get the one over r squared
i don't believe there is
uh for that
that's equivalent to knowledge of the
distribution of energies and
it doesn't fit anything simple it's not
a boltzmann distribution
so i i don't think there's any simple
way
as far as i know it is not known exactly
why the distribution is what it is
now there's lots and lots and lots of
simulations and i don't know what the
state of the art is
with gravitational lensing if it was
diffuse you could try and measure it
that way if it's a significant portion
of the mass you'd have like twice the
lensing effect when you like trying to
like
image yeah you know galaxies behind it
or around it or something like that oh
yeah you can uh you can
yes the lensing due to galaxies uh
sensitive to them is that what you're
saying it's sensitive to the mass
absolutely you'd have like a relative
effect if you took a look at the optical
mass and or radiation and then
it would be significantly larger so dark
matter causes lensing right it does oh
yeah
dark matter is part of the mass which
causes lensing
so it's
uh is there something to suggest in in
observation that
byway and lensing you can discern
the distribution of dark i'm sure there
is but i'm not an expert at it but i'm
sure there is i mean that's uh that's a
very obvious thing to try to do is to uh
map out uh
map out the dark matter by
an lensing
where they looked at galaxies that were
colliding
and
the base
because the the visible matter interacts
with those stars
populations of stars interact
um
you get
basically two hypotheses about how the
the lensing
and
um
the evidence seems to be that there's uh
i guess a different a different lensing
effect because the
the dark matter doesn't interact
in the same way are you talking about
the bullet galaxy yeah the
the bullet cluster is uh it's a pair of
galactic clusters that are interacting
yeah right the gas on the inside which
is regular matter is hot and seen in
x-rays and then you can measure the
distribution of the total matter by
looking at gravitational lensing
so you get a distribution of total
matter and
a distribution of
normal matter and what's left over is
assumed to be dark matter the point is
that when the two
galaxies collided
uh the ordinary material interacted in a
significant way
the dark matter clouds just interacted
gravitationally and was not such a
significant interaction and the result
was a separation of dark matter from
from the other matter
and so
there's an example
the controversy had to do with whether
there really was dark matter
or whether newton's
or einstein's gravitational theory had
to be modified
you could try to
fit the rotation curves of galaxies by
modifying newton's force law we got it
from newton's force law where is it over
here
by modifying newton's force law
uh
and in that picture there really
wouldn't be dark matter
or
the the gravitating effect
would be modified but it would still be
attached to the same masses
um
[Music]
it would be quite clear that that would
not be a good description
if it was possible to separate dark
matter from the ordinary matter
okay
and apparently in these bullet clusters
this is bullet cluster two galaxies
collided and the effect was a separation
of the dark matter from the luminous
matter
and so that kind of settled the
controversy of whether uh of whether
there is dark matter
or whether it's a
simply a modification of newton's law
is the numerous method only referred to
the dc perspective
no
no any way that you can see it any way
you can see it optically by any way that
you can see it um electromagnetically
but yeah i think in first approximation
yes it was the visible the visible light
the visible light
for the most part
but the original hypothesis was that
light
that mass followed light that
the luminosity
was a good measure of the
abundance of mass
field
well i think we would have noticed if it
emitted any appreciable amount of
radiation into other uh
no it's possible that dark matter for
example annihilates and creates gamma
rays
right
sure
sure but that you wouldn't see through
ordinary telescopes you see in particle
detectors and
right good okay
continuity
well the two they seem to be two very
different things they don't seem to be
uh
but um
very little is known
what i would say about dark matter is
very little is known in detail about
what it is
but it's entirely consistent it doesn't
require any
radical modifications of the rules
[Music]
that there are more particles than have
yet been discovered i think we all
believe
um
we've probably just touched the surface
of all of the particles that exist
and that there are particles which can
be very weakly interacting we already
know there are
neutrinos as we've mentioned
and so without doing any radical damage
to any of the principles of physics we
can easily accommodate dark matter by
just saying it's particles that we
haven't discovered yet
[Music]
well that sounds funny but it's probably
what it is
it's probably what it is it gives every
indication of not being anything
radically different
and since
everybody and his brother has postulated
a particle for one reason or another
and often for very very good reasons
there are probably more particles many
of them we can weakly interacting and
it's probably what they are
if not not but
[Music]
wasn't there a thought that there's a
lot of hydrogen you can't see unionized
hydrogen that kind of made up this mass
it seems to me that wasn't there was a
time when people thought that it might
be
just hydrogen
there was a time nobody thinks that
anymore
and i think at least one of the reasons
is because the amount of it
is so large that it would have radically
affected the creation of helium and then
the early universe and radically
affected the nuclear physics of the
first three minutes in some really uh
awkward way
so that's uh there's just too much of it
to fit into any uh
when we talk about nuclear synthesis
we'll talk about that a little bit
there's too much of it
and is there or not any evidence that
dark matter has either electrical or
magnetic properties well the evidence is
it doesn't have very much
that they're not
yeah
they're probably neutral
they
certainly don't have any significant
electric charge
the standard model has no uh
doesn't talk to the the any pops
possible model does not have particles
of this type
the supersymmetric standard model has a
thousand of them you know all over the
place and uh so
sometimes people regard this as
evidence or weak evidence of
supersymmetry
that's a that's a bit of a stretch but
it could be
but there's a lot of there's a lot of
good reasons you know it's really
sensible reasons for thinking that there
are more particles
and so
the dark matter could be
any one of them it could be a
combination of them
[Music]
i think we'll find out i think that's
not not out of the
question to find out in the next 10
years
[Music]